We start with I never remember.  With
what?  What do we start with?
We start
theoretically with
services and processes.  We start with
data access.  Okay, very good.  Let's go to
data access.
Let's go to data access.  Okay, we were
working the other day.
Let's see.  Oh, how strange.
Handling connectors.
Okay.  Holy [ __ ], wait.
File management.
Job.  Cop.
I'm in the right place.
Let's see for
a moment.
Access methods.  Okay.
Classes for this.  Okay.  Letters.  Okay,
file operations, hashes and
sequential.  Okay.  Serialization and
deserialization.  Okay.  Working with
files.  Okay.
Exceptions and developing applications
that use files.  Okay, let's go for
it.
The objective in this case is to create a
small connector that works with
files and allows us
to understand each other. Let's make a
CSV storage engine, okay?  Let's go,
we're going to work
with a small MySQL engine, but for
CSV files, so 001
Python introduction.  Let's start with Python and
now we'll see later, now later I'd
like to transform this into a
C++ program, okay?  And so we make an
executable connector.
Okay, so let's do
a simulation
of the
CSV connector.
The thing is, it sounds to me like we
were working with
relational mapping last week.
But I don't know, I don't know in what part of my
brain that happened.
Desfase objeto relacional y por qué me
he saltado yo estas unidades.
In the end.  Okay, well, nothing, come on.  Okay,
CSV, I was saying,
what is a CSV?  Well, you already know that a
CSV is a file that allows us to
enter rows and columns, right?  So
if I want to have
clients, for example, I have the first name, comma,
last name, comma, and email, comma,
address,
okay?  And now I have José Vicente, comma
Carratalá, comma
milk, comma info@josicente
or info@jocarsa.com,
José Vicente's street.  Okay, the idea
is that next, not in ORM
like last week, but directly
in relational, I want a way to
save this information.  What I am going
to show you now, in fact, is not
either.  Look, eh, Damian.  And come on,
perfect.  Oh look, and it just got
fixed.  Ah, okay.  Okay, so, uh,
Myers SQL, if you look at MySQL, if I
enter a table, well, in fact, CSV is
one of the engines that MySQL has.
So, what I want in
today's class is the following.
I want to create
a file, save data in
csv.python format.
Okay, what are we going to do?  Well,
I want tuple equal to some data, some
data that will be eh José Vicente
comma Carratalá.
Oh, blame Carratalá and
info@jocarsa.com.
And now what I want is to save this
to a file.  For example, I'm going to do
hm file equals open
clients.Csv
and I want it in write mode, I want it or
in appen mode, for example.  So
file.
And I want and I want and I want and I want and I
want em
What do I want?  Well, I want to write
the tuple, but of course, this is going to give me an
error, of course.  So file
point close.
Okay, let's run it.
Let's run it.  I'm going to Dam. I'm going to the
second one, I'm going to data access,
file management, working with files
and
then
we're going to save that tuple and most
likely I'm going to get an error because
Python 30002
save, okay?  And he'll say, "No, you have to
save a string, you can't save
a tuple, okay? What can I
do?"  Well, I can serialize and
deserialize, okay?  So to
save in the tuple
what I can do is ah string
equals nothing and for field
in tuple.  This is the part I love about
Python: string plus equals field plus
a comma.
So here we go.   We
run again.  Hey, no, yeah, sure.
Chain.
And now 003. We serialize.
Okay.  And I want to save the chain,
so we do it like this.  Hey, hey, let's
see.  No, tuple, what are you telling me?
archive.  Tuple, it's not that I want
Python 3003.
Okay, now I do have CSV clients and what
I just did is convert a
tuple or a list or I don't care what
inside a CSV file, okay?  with
which I have a kind of,
so to speak, I have a kind of
insert.
In this way, I could now
become a reader, a
writer.  Now I want to read 004,
deserialize,
which would then lead to
this, okay?  We would go to an
application like this.  The only thing
is that this is a JSON.  So now what
I'm doing is
file equals open clients CSV in
read mode and eh let's look at it
and I want to deserialize.
So line equals file.
Readline
and then I say tuple equals line
dot split with comma.
Uh, print tuple or list, because it
really is a list.
I'm going to say tuple and I'm going to say print
type tuple
so we can see that it's not really a tuple
.
So Python 3 004
and okay, I have it converted there and it
tells me that it's a list, which I don't
care about because I convert it to a tuple, I
convert it to a tuple.  And then I say,
eh, tuple equals tuple
of tuple.  And then I say print tuple and
type tuple.
Python 005.
Okay, now it's a tuple.
That means that from here,
as you can imagine, what I
can do is convert this into a
connector, uh, make
a class, okay?  For example, let's
see it,
let's do it quickly because I want to
get to the next exercise, which is the
really cool one,
okay?  and eh I come over here
and say,
"Take this eh writer
and this reader
and create a class with two methods."
And then next I say 006 class
with two methods.
Okay, so called CSV manager
and I have this, okay?  I have the class and it
looks much more elegant, okay?  I have
writing and I have reading, which
basically does the same thing.  And I have a
demonstration,
okay?  And I have a usage demo
where I can create a new
CSV manager instance just like someone who creates a new
MySQL instance and from there
I have the write method and the
read method, right?  What are you going to give me, in fact,
we are going to execute him.
Where are you saving?  To CSV clients.   I
can also modify it, okay?  and
Python 3
eh 006.
Okay, and I have the same thing there.  Okay, but
today, apart from reviewing
work with files, there's one thing
I'm really interested in, which I think is an
exercise you'll really enjoy, which
is reviewing the power of Python to
process large file systems,
okay?  Big data.  So
for that, in this same subunit, for
a moment, I'm going to fold in some other things
to focus on.
In this subunit, what I want to do is
use Python to process an entire
file system and
obtain information from it.  And what's going on
here?  No, without saving and out.
Vale,
entonces voy a hacer un nuevo archivo.
review tree.  recursive directory structure in
Python and there are new libraries in Python
in recent versions that
specifically do this.  Hey, Python
Pars directore
recursive,
okay?  And that's it, okay, this is
imports.
Okay, and the route and the route that I'm going to
put is, for example, well, look,
bar
w html and eh DAM 2526,
okay?  which is the folder we are
working on here in the cycle.  Well, let's
see.  Let's see it.  I now
proceed to execute.
I run Python 3 and eh 007
and it goes back.  Okay, this appears.  Very
good.
Within each directory.  It's going
into each directory and
telling me what's there.
So from here on there are 1 million
things we can do.  And
then in this class I'm going to
develop a bunch of components that I
think are going to be useful and not
useful to you throughout the rest of the course
for a billion things.  So I'm going
to do the following.  008 and we'll see.   file
tree
files
and directories
okay.  And then I say the following.
Print directory for sub in
subdirectories.  Okay, so I'm going to do
level equals 0.
And now every time I go up a level,
level plus equals 1. And then I say
subdirectory sub and
level
is uh the syntax, you know, for
formatting level and file.  Archive.  Okay.
So if this is true,
Python 3 008
008.
Okay.  And we'll see.
Wow.  Ah, no, no, no, no, sorry, sorry,
sorry, sorry.
No, it's counting, counting,
counting directories, right?  Let's see.
What I want is Let's
see.
for sub in subdirectories.  I don't want to
catch the level.  Moment.
I want to get level
depth level.
Oh, that
and where is this.
Okay,
let's go.
Now yes, okay.  Level 6, level 5, level
6 and so on.  Okay, next, I
like this.  What I want is to
keep the last element of a URL
, okay?  So, the last
element, let's look at it.
This is directory.  Let's see, directory,
subdirectory, right?  Ah, no, directory.
Host.  Ah.  Subdirectory.  Okay.
And directory
and subdirectory.  But
exercises.  Exercises.  Okay, I don't want
the subdirectory.   I
want this out.
009. I don't want the subdirectory, I
think.
Okay.
Python 009.
Okay, perfect.  Now yes.  Okay,
now next,
if I have the level,
what I want to do is format the string
as many spaces as the level has.
So,
for,
let's see, for this in range from zero to
level.
Another thing I can do, sorry, is
more beastly.   I
take off the F
and call it space
multiplied by level.  Let's see if
this works for me.  Sometimes it works.  And
directory.
Oh, well, I don't want the print format,
okay?
and level.  Well, more space,
more level,
more level.
And the most that can happen to me is that
this has to be a STR.
Okay.  Okay.  Let's try it and see if it doesn't
explode too much.  This, what is it?
This is 010 formatting
and uh Python 3 010.
Okay.
Okay.  This is starting to work,
okay?  The dirty trick worked for me, which
is basically putting a space
in multiplied by the level, okay?
which is a very dirty Python trick,
but it worked for me.  And now
next here, okay?  Directory and
level level five, okay?  In fact, you
could put two spaces, then it will make
double.  And now the file.
So in the file I'm going to do the
same thing,
print.
And this utility, I insist, I mean, you
can save it because you're going to
use it a lot, but a lot, 1000,
okay?  So
uh level plus
level + 1 multiplied
by two spaces times
two spaces, okay?  More
file
and that's it.  And this is going out.
Okay.  And let's see if we put
011 file
and see if we can keep the code
as simple as possible.  Python 3011.
Fantastic.
Okay, good, good.  Two and two.
Very good.  Okay, below
the folders, you can see how the folder
structure is now appearing here
.  I would like not to have
the whole route, I would like to have only the
final part.  Well, there is a way to
do it which is directory split points
of slash
and -1.  -1 is keep the last one, another
dirty Python trick.  So I run.
This is something else,
okay?  So here, as you can see, he
's taking out a tree from me.  Then the level
doesn't matter, I can take it off now.
I can remove the level now.
Okay.
And now,
well, one thing I can do, for
example, is to use emojis to distinguish between
a folder and a
file.
So eh let's put 012 emojis.
Hey, I'm going to go to
emojis.jocarsa.com.
I'm going to put file.  Well, it's not
any of them.  Y folder, mira.  Folder.  Yes.
Okay, so this is a folder.
Oh, and no, wait, this is a folder,
okay?  Eat
emoji.
And this is clear, file,
but file.
Ah, I'm looking to see if there's any
Mira, this one, for example.  This one is already done.
It will be as a document,
okay?  more
more eh emoji more file.  Okay,
technically if you want to do it the
same way, we're going to do it the same way
and use the console.
Wait, this is Python 3 012 emojis.  Oh,
and this already looks cool.  Okay.  And
now next, And now
next, before
before each of the emojis, I'm going to
put an L. Okay, I guess you know
what I mean.  I'm going to put an L like
a bar, like an arm, I think it's
called, an arm elbow, which is the
next one.  Hey, let's see.  I do
n't think it will be here
because I think it is an ASCI character.
Okay, asci table.
Easy tables.
Aha, aha, aha.   It
is one of the advanced ones.
Yeah.  Well no.
Wow,
weird.
Let's see, as tables,
eh, elbow, the elbow.
There's one that's an Oh, no,
uh, over here, over here, over here.  Yes,
but [ __ ], but don't give me an
image.  But these are these are these
are.  Okay, let's see.
Yes, but no.  Extended.
As table.  Extended.
Extended.
This, this is starting to appear.  This
is what I want.  Here you are.  Okay.
I want, I want, I want
this theoretically,
okay?  I insist, it is a
legal ASCI character, so theoretically it
should be supported.
So let's put in asci.
013. We enter Asti,
okay?  And in the file, before the
file, I want to put this and in the
directory I want to put this.  But but
I'm going to run
Python 3, I don't remember anymore,
uh, 013.
Okay, fine.  Okay.  Oh,
wow.
Oh, yeah.
Okay,
[Music]
okay.  The one in the folder is correct,
but of course, now I need these
characters.
Okay, the one in the file isn't the correct one
because the one in the file is this one,
which isn't entirely true either, but
okay.
Uh, that, that, that, right?  No, let's see, I've
also done, okay, that, okay?  A
lot of times with an arrow stick.
Look, Fran, as you can imagine, I
want this for several reasons, many
reasons.  It's a software that we're going to
use later as a
reusable component in a lot of places.  One
of them is AI, okay?  Honestly,
you already see me coming.
And so, what I want to tell you is
that the AI ​​doesn't care if you put
pipe sticks and pipes up
and such, or if you do it in Asti because
it will understand you.  What happens is that
in the same way that I put an emoji
to make it look nice and well, it's
also better if we put astis because
then both on a visual level it looks cool
because for example, as you can
imagine, we are going to make a
software that makes software reports,
okay?  That is, documentation and of course,
the documentation will look cooler
asci than you know what characters
alone, but as I said, it
could be done, right?  And now what I
want And now what I want is that
from here to here there is a
vertical character, okay?  Yes,
nothing happens, nothing happens.  So the
vertical character, the vertical character
we're going to mix
here.  Okay,
sure, level plus a no.  What I want
is 014, eh, we enter vertical asci
and I say level plus one, no.  This over here.
Now I want the vertical asci
which is
correct.  This, this is the
vertical one, okay?
This, two spaces.  Ah, look, this is not
necessary.  And this two spaces.  Okay,
let's try it.
I'm gone.  Yes. Python 30 14.
Oh,
how could I not?  Something done wrong.  Yes.
Oh yes, sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry.
Okay,
this two spaces plus this.  Now yes.
Let's see it.
Okay, this looks different now.  Very
good.  In the Ah, just a moment, just a
moment.  Sure, this helps me for the
last one.
Aquí también en las carpetas podría
meter esta menos en la última.
Okay.
Okay.  And now this happens.  It turns out
I'm only seeing the last folder,
but I should see the others as well.
to put the others in too.  Oh,
wait, wait, wait, Miguel Ángel,
you'll see, you'll see,
because now I'm going to want to
know how many kilobytes each file takes up
and all that, okay?  Now I'm going to want to
extract information and then I'll also
tell you, okay? Later on,
I'm working with emojis now, but
depending on the extension I could change
the icon a little bit like Windows, okay?
But I insist, Mil Ángel, we are
doing this beautifully, but not just to make it
beautiful, but later, for example,
when I feed an
artificial intelligence a project and
say, "Tell me what this project is about."
Okay, now we'll see.  Let's continue.
Okay, so I'm going to put in the following.
I think I'm going to put in a pipe with
space.  Okay, I think I'll try
this.  So, I do this.  Let's see.
Oh, okay, it works fine with the files
, but it doesn't work well for me.  It's the other
way around.  is pipe and space.  Well, pipe
that's how it is.
Okay.  And now, and now, and now I
need him here too.
Okay, this is something else.  This already
looks different.
Good.  And we're going to see it.  Let's see it.
Okay, now we have to touch on a few
things,
although things are already starting to get
here.
It is, for example, here.
Hey,
yeah, useful.  Yes.
Okay, but once I've made
clear what I want,
now what I want, for example, is for
the last file not to have this one, but to
have the elbow one, okay?  But I
can leave that to the AI ​​once
we've made it clear what we
want.  For example, this last
folder has an elbow and doesn't continue, okay?
Okay.  And this one here, for example,
has an elbow and doesn't continue.  Okay.  Come on,
perfect.  But I insist, above all you,
Miguel Ángel, you said, "How beautiful,
right? For me, this is the beautiful thing. For me,
the beautiful thing is being able to do this and having the
code as minimal as possible. Okay,
let's see if it doesn't make a mess of things
. Let's see if we're lucky.
So,
let's see. I would like to
enhance this drawing
elbows,
for example,
in the in the
last elements of a folder, use emojis, and so on.
Let's see.
And Fran, that's what I mean, okay? That's
the magic of Python, that's the
beauty of Python. And it's that really,
as I always tell you, these
are really five lines because
the whole story is in here, okay? But that,
for me, is the beautiful thing, being able to make
a component that we then have to
encapsulate in a function,
obviously. Okay, let's see. Well,
the invention went to hell, but okay, it was
clear that it was going to happen, no problem. And
probably, well, it's that
GPT is like that, [ __ ]. And  It's clear, it
immediately creates
control structures for me, it creates defensive programming
for me so that eventually,
in the case of uncontrolled assumptions
, which is not this case, in the
case of not having permission, I can put
all this and such, okay? But well,
fine, fine, I like it.
Fine. Okay, 015 extending.
Okay.
And here we go. Okay, if it's last, then
print this one for me. And if not,
print this one for me. Okay. Okay. Let's
try it.
Hey, Python 3 and I don't remember anything.
015.
Okay, of course, obviously, now
this is prettier,
okay?
Okay,
now next. Okay
. Okay
. Okay. Now next
I'm going to say save it for me, I mean,
sorry, encapsulate it for me. It
's a draw 3. Okay,
it's already encapsulated. Ah, look, this
is the route.
Okay,
but there's a problem. There's a problem is
that everything is doing a print and
you know  I always tell you that
prints in programming are kind of
forbidden, okay? Print shouldn't
be inside a function. I
say,
"Okay, I like it."
But please transform all functions
to return
and leave print to the usage.
I might need to
save it to disk
instead. Okay, so the idea is don't
print me, just return me, and then
I'll decide if I put it in the
database, if I print it, if I print it to the
screen or send it to HTML or whatever
I want. Okay? So, what do I
always tell you? That is that
functions don't print, but rather
return.
Let's see if I've received any
more emails, although I doubt it, although I
doubt it, it's not worth it because it's in the
afternoon.
Okay, so now I come here,
this is 016 return instead of print,
okay, and print to screen or save to file.
Okay, so let's go. 016
Python 3 016.
Okay,  Okay, okay. But it also
converted it to 3.txt,
right? That's exactly the trick. And
from here, I have this as
a file in a function that I
can then externalize to a
Python file and then I can use it for
whatever we want. And for whatever we want,
for example, to give you an example today, it
would be taking this,
putting it into an
artificial intelligence, which I don't think would be very interesting
there. And now, wait,
let's do something. I'm going to put
this, the file directly.
Copy, paste to the desktop so I can
pass it to GPT chat.
Okay, I do this and I say, "Tell me
what's happening here."
With which, reading documents,
hierarchical dump,
okay? Modules appear like
databases, each module is subdivided into
units, numbered units, blah blah blah blah
blah. Okay? And then, as
you know, especially those of you who
had me last year, you
know that I have a software called eh
Light  Yellow Golden Road or Light Golden
Road Yellow, which in
a second pass asks for the
specific content of each file and
in the specific content of each
file, it puts the content there.
Okay? Good. So,
for now, we're going to dedicate the rest
of the class, well, yes, more or less the
rest of the class to programming, that
is, programming services and
processes, okay? So, as you
can imagine, in the next
data access class, we'll program a
component that tells me what this
file has, and what we'll be doing in the
end is a bit of reprogramming the software I have
from last year, the Light
Golden Road Yellow, okay? Do you
also remember the software from
last year? From Tomato, right? From Tomato, it was
for monitoring the server
that made chocolate, okay? Do you
remember Chocolate? It was a
software for documenting
projects, which is, tell me what hierarchy
a project has, tell me what's inside
each file, and in this course, with the
help and intelligence  Artificial: Read
the project, read the file,
document the project for me, that is,
document both each
individual file and what the
project does. And the goal in the end is to
use data access techniques
combined with artificial intelligence,
for example, to get rid of the
heaviest part of a project, which is
precisely documenting. Okay, come on,
this way. Wow, Luis, you're
doing great. Okay, just a moment
because we're just about to make the
class change.